Guide to the George L. Gardaya papers, 1925-1955 M2097
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
George L. Gardaya papers
1925-1955
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Michael Brown Rare Books
Gardaya, George L., 1902-1968
M2097
0.834 Linear Feet (2 legal manuscript boxes and 1 oversize map folder)
The collection includes correspondence, poetry and verse (some in Ilocano), school work including essays, graded papers and notes, and ephemera. It is comprised of both typescript and manuscript pages. Also in the collection are documents for the Philippines Cooperative Association in New York. Some of the material is signed by probable pseudonyms of Gardaya, including Segundo Lagoc Gardaya and Gregory Francis D'Mayo.
Many pages very fragile, poor quality paper.
Biographical Note
George L. Gardaya (1902-1968), was an emigrant to America from the Philippines. Gardaya was involved in Philippine-American organizations in New York City. He appears to have been gay or bisexual, and lived with a man named Peter Martinez for a number of years, though he married a woman later in life. Gardaya was a native of Pasuquin, Ilocos Norte, Philippine Islands and New York City, New York. Hew was also a student, poet, and Secretary of the Philippines' Co-Operative Association, a.k.a Philamer House. In 1933 he seems to have founded a perfume company. He used a number of pseudonyms including Segundo Lagoc Gardaya, Gregory Francis Tamayo, Franz de Mayo, or Gregory Francis D'Mayo.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 2015 by Stanford University Libraries.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence, some partial drafts, some love letters (most to women, but some are written to men); poetry, verse, and prose presumably written by Gardaya; typed and manuscript pages and documents for the Philamer Cooperative Association, including about a dozen biographical applications of members, constitution, etc. There is also a typed copy of the Constitution for the Filipino Club of the Bronx, a worker's organization of the Bronx Hospital, New York, where Gardaya worked, dated circa 1930s. A play titled "Tongues of Despair: a Drama with a Female Lead," by Gregory Francis D'Mayo (an apparent pseudonym of Gardaya), which appears to have been submitted to Fox Film Corporation at one point. School notes, essays, papers, some finished and graded, others drafts, some typed, some school printed forms, all school related, presumably when Gardaya was attending Cornell and Columbia University, circa 1929-1937. Ephemera (printed, some manuscript), including brochures, circulars, greeting cards, blue print, map, newspaper clippings, drawings, news- letter, etc.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Note that material must be requested at least 36 hours in advance of intended use.
Filipino Americans; Gardaya, George L., 1902-1968
- Correspondence, 1928-1955 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Love letters, typescript, 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letter to Aunt Leliany (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Letters to Eddie, 1931 [?] - 1932 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Letters - drafts - manuscripts, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Philamer Cooperative Association - constitution and by-laws (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Philamer Cooperative Association - correspondence and biographical applications of members (Box 1, Folder 5)
- George L. Gardaya, pseudonym, - poetry and verse (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Gregory Francis D'Mayo, pseudonym, - poetry (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Gregory Francis D'Mayo, pseudonym, - short stories (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Gregory Francis D'Mayo - synopsis of play: Tongues of Despair: a drama with a female lead (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ephemera: brochures, circulars, greeting cards, newspaper clippings, publications (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Two sketeches of a female head; sheet music and ukelele lessons (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Unidentified fragment of manuscript (Box 1, Folder 11)
- George L. Gardaya, Pastor L. Gardaya, Jr. [psudonyms?]: school work including essays, compositions, notes, Spanish grammer (Box 2, Folder 1)
- School work: essays, papers, compositions, notes (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
- School work: essays and graded papers, October - December 1934 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- School work: essays and graded papers, October - December 1934 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- School work: essays about humus, soil, water (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Map of the Philippines, March 1945 (Map-folder 3)
- Blueprint of automatic cigarette dispenser, March 1931 (Map-folder 3)
- Tree of life sketches (Map-folder 3)
- New York Post, Monday June 29, 1936,p 11 (Map-folder 3)
- Home study music lessons: ukulele; sheet music: My own, music by Jimmy McHugh, lyric by Harold Adamson (Map-folder 3)